It is a most miserable thing to feel ashamed of home.
There may be black ingratitude in the thing, and the punishment may be
retributive and well deserved; but that it is a miserable thing, I can testify.
Home had never been a very pleasant place to me, because of my sister’s temper. But,
Joe had sanctified it, and I had believed in it. I had believed in the best parlour as a most elegant
saloon; I had believed in the front door, as a mysterious portal of the Temple of State whose
solemn opening was attended with a sacrifice of roast fowls; I had believed in the kitchen as
a chaste though not magnificent apartment; I had believed in the forge as the glowing
road to manhood and independence. Within a single year all this was changed. Now it was
all coarse and common, and I would not have had Miss Havisham and Estella see it on any account.
How much of my ungracious condition of mind may have been my own fault,
how much Miss Havisham’s, how much my sister’s, is now of no moment to me or to any one. The
change was made in me; the thing was done. Well or ill done, excusably or inexcusably, it was done.
Once, it had seemed to me that when I should at last roll up my shirt-sleeves and go into the
forge, Joe’s ’prentice, I should be distinguished and happy. Now the reality was in my hold,
I only felt that I was dusty with the dust of small-coal, and that I had a weight upon
my daily remembrance to which the anvil was a feather. There have been occasions in my
later life (I suppose as in most lives) when I have felt for a time as if a thick curtain
had fallen on all its interest and romance, to shut me out from anything save dull endurance
any more. Never has that curtain dropped so heavy and blank, as when my way in life lay
stretched out straight before me through the newly entered road of apprenticeship to Joe.
I remember that at a later period of my “time,” I used to stand about the churchyard on Sunday
evenings when night was falling, comparing my own perspective with the windy marsh view,
and making out some likeness between them by thinking how flat and low both were,
and how on both there came an unknown way and a dark mist and then the sea. I was
quite as dejected on the first working-day of my apprenticeship as in that after-time;
but I am glad to know that I never breathed a murmur to Joe while my indentures lasted.
It is about the only thing I am glad to know of myself in that connection.
For, though it includes what I proceed to add, all the merit of what I proceed to add was Joe’s. It
was not because I was faithful, but because Joe was faithful, that I never ran away and went for
a soldier or a sailor. It was not because I had a strong sense of the virtue of industry,
but because Joe had a strong sense of the virtue of industry, that I worked with tolerable zeal
against the grain. It is not possible to know how far the influence of any amiable
honest-hearted duty-doing man flies out into the world; but it is very possible to know how it has
touched one’s self in going by, and I know right well that any good that intermixed itself with
my apprenticeship came of plain contented Joe, and not of restlessly aspiring discontented me.
What I wanted, who can say? How can I say, when I never knew? What I dreaded was,
that in some unlucky hour I, being at my grimiest and commonest, should lift up my
eyes and see Estella looking in at one of the wooden windows of the forge. I was haunted by
the fear that she would, sooner or later, find me out, with a black face and hands,
doing the coarsest part of my work, and would exult over me and despise me. Often after dark,
when I was pulling the bellows for Joe, and we were singing Old Clem, and when the thought how
we used to sing it at Miss Havisham’s would seem to show me Estella’s face in the fire,
with her pretty hair fluttering in the wind and her eyes scorning me,—often at such a time I
would look towards those panels of black night in the wall which the wooden windows then were, and
would fancy that I saw her just drawing her face away, and would believe that she had come at last.
After that, when we went in to supper, the place and the meal would have a more
homely look than ever, and I would feel more ashamed of home than ever,
in my own ungracious breast. Chapter 15.